我生来便是英格兰的郡长
(UHTRED) I was born an ealdorman of England.
诺森布里亚贝班堡领地的正统继承人
True heir to the Northumbrian lands of Bebbanburg.
我十二岁第一次上战场
I was 12 years old when I Hrst went to war.
亲眼看着父亲战死
I saw my father killed.
我和撒克逊女孩布丽达被入侵者掳走
Stolen by the invaders, along with the Saxon girl Brida,
我先做了奴隶，后来成了拉格纳伯爵的养子
I became Hrst a slave, and then a son to Earl Ragnar.
命运让我变成了丹麦人
Fate had made me a Dane.
命运让小拉格纳成了我兄弟, 让布丽达成了我的爱人
It made Young Rag/var my brother, and Bride my lover.
- 而后命运带来了背叛 - 着火了!
- And then fate brought betrayal. - Fire!
谣言四起, 说是我杀了拉格纳
Lies were thrown to the wind saying I had killed Ragnar.
我们带着他藏的财物, 一路往南
(UHTRED) So taking his hidden wealth, we fled south...
逃向威塞克斯, 逃向贝奥卡
To Wessex, to Beocca,
逃向国王的兄弟阿尔弗雷德
and to the king's brother Alfred.
丹麦人把我当撒克逊人, 撒克逊人把我当丹麦人
Seen by the Danes as a Saxon and by Saxons as a Dane,
没有人信我的话
my word could not be trusted.
但我是乌特雷德, 乌特雷德之子
But I am Uhtred, son of Uhtred,
命运主宰一切
and destiny is all.
- 让开路 - 闪开! 是国王!
- (MAN) Clear the way. - Stand clear! It is the king!
大人, 我必须说, 那斧子砍得很深
(ODDA) I have to speak, lord. The axe cut deep.
- 就算是国王也撑不住 - 我们祈祷, 静待结果
- Even a king couldn't survive. - We shall pray and we shall see.
大人, 抱歉
Apologies, lord,
在没有事先和阿尔佛雷德商量之前, 我只能做这么多了
this was the best I could do without first speaking to Alfred.
我带来了食物和麦酒
I have brought food and ale,
- 更重要的是, 有好消息 - 阿尔弗雷德死了?
,- and more importantly, good news. - Alfred is dead?
恰恰相反, 他活着, 而且赢了
The opposite. He is alive and he is victorious.
我们击败了丹麦人
We defeated the Danes.
- 这算什么好消息？- 阿尔弗雷德采纳了你的建议
- Why is this good news? - Alfred acted upon your advice.
- 你也分享了他的荣耀 - 荣耀？
- You share in his glory. - (BRIDA) Glory?
那他为什么被关在笼子里，只能蹲在角落里解手？
Then why is he caged and left to shit in the corner?
你管这叫荣耀？
You call that glory?
她就不能闭一会儿嘴吗？
Can she not hold her tongue for just one moment?
不，她不能，也不会！
No she cannot and she will not!
- 把你的食物留着！- 只有阿尔弗雷德
- Keep your food! - (BEOCCA) Only Alfred
- 我不吃也不喝！- 只有阿尔弗雷德能下令放你
- (BRIDA) I will not eat or drink! - Only Alfred can order your release.
我去跟他谈
I will speak with him.
姑娘，你应该趁这段时间好好反省一下自己
You should spend this time, girl, to contemplate improvement.
我要用这段时间来诅咒你
I will use this time to curse you.
- 那就诅咒吧 - 阿尔弗雷德拒绝了我的效忠
- Then do it. - Alfred refused my sword.
除非他来求我，否则我不会再开口
I won't be offering it again unless he begs.
大人，我怀疑你这股倔劲
Lord, I wonder whether your pig-headedness
不过是蠢到家了
is not simple stupidity.
等他把铠甲上的泥和血刮干净，就会派人来找你
He'll send for you when he has scraped the mud and blood from his mail.
我们要向奥丁感恩，感谢他护佑我们
(BRIDA) We will give thanks to Odin for our deliverance.
你这么做吧
(BEOCCA) Do that.
我们是丹麦人！
(BRIDA) We are Danes!
放尊重点
(GUARD) Show respect!
再来一次，我就割断你的喉咙
Do it again, and I will cut you cock to throat.
你是威塞克斯的英雄
You are a hero of Wessex.
恭喜你
Congratulations.
我们还活着
We're alive.
什么事
(ALFRED) what is it?
我等不及要见你
(AELSWITH) I couldn't wait to see you.
有人告诉我你平安无事, 但我要亲眼看到才放心
I was told you are safe, but I needed proof.
现在看到了
Here it is.
- 你们都退下, 我妻子来帮我 - 是, 大人
-Leave us. My wife will help me. -My lord.
这是我的荣幸
My privilege.
把它好好修补, 仔细点
Ensure it is repaired, and well.
没有你我就是个不知所措的傻瓜
I'd be a lost fool without you.
哈, 笨手笨脚的
Heh. Fingers and thumbs.
谁在敲门?
Who knocks?
大人
(BEOCCA) My lord.
夫人, 打扰了
My lady. Forgive me.
我想趁这会儿谈谈郡长乌特雷德的事
I was, hoping for a moment to discuss the Ealdorman Uhtred.
神父, 恕我直言, 大人需要休息了
Father, forgive me, but my lord is in need of rest.
确实
He is.
你也需要休息...
You are, um...
抱歉
Forgive me.
埃塞尔沃尔德
(YOUNGER) Aethelwold.
你在山岗上吗? 我没见到你
Were you on the hill? I didn't see you?
我被留在神父那边, 没有上去
I was kept safe with the priests.
以后还有很多仗要打
There will be other battles, many.
会没完没了的, 直到我们全死光为止
And on and on it will go, I'm sure, until we are all dead.
- 你是说我们该投降? - 绝不
- You saying we should surrender? - Never.
绝不
Never.
但我并不反对妥协
But I am not against compromise.
我虽敬爱天主, 却不急着去见他
As much as I love my God, I am in no hurry to reach heaven.
就算跪满一地的神父
I fear no number of kneeling clergy men
也改变不了异教徒的斧头已经定下的结局
will change what a heathen's axe has already decreed.
我们该为国王的继承人祈祷
Our prayers should be with the king's successor.
王冠是我的, 这是我与生俱来的权利
The crown is mine, my birth right.
你有异议?
You disagree?
有人会说您年纪太轻, 大人
The argument will be that you are young, lord.
- 我是父亲的继承人 - 您是父亲的继承人,
- I am my father's heir. - You are your father's heir,
但阿尔佛雷德是你父亲的兄弟
but your father was also bonded to Alfred.
儿子比兄弟先
A son comes before a brother.
那您或许应该直接去找国王谈
Then perhaps you should speak to the king directly.
我是这么想的, 大人,
'Tis my thinking, lord,
若您父亲在临终前能亲口点名让您继位,
that if on his death bed your father were to name you as his successor,
贤人会议就很难违逆他的意愿
the Witan would find it difficult to go against him.
我相信您父亲会很乐意附在您耳边说那句话的,
I believe your father would only be too happy to whisper in your ear,
不管他当时是否清醒
whether he was conscious or not.
你的建言我不会忘, 小奥达
Your counsel will not be forgotten, Young Odda.
谢谢您, 大人
Thank you, lord.
古思伦, 你没等我就出兵了
(UBBA) Guthrum, you went into battle without me.
为什么?
Why was that?
那不是本来的打算
That was not the intention.
是吗?
Is that so?
那为什么还是发生了?
Then why did it happen?
- 进去说 - 就在这儿说
- Let's talk inside. - We will talk here.
他们出兵比我们预料的早,
They marched sooner than we expected,
而且在山上占了好位置
and they positioned themselves well on the hill.
- 这种事不会再发生 - 不会再发生了
- It will not happen again. - It will not happen again
因为你的人已经折损了一半
because you have lost half your men.
我们杀了他们的国王，埃塞尔雷德
We killed their king, Aethelred.
- 你亲眼看见他倒下了？ - 是，我亲眼看见的,
- Did you see him fall? - Yeah, I saw him fall,
一斧头劈下去，死透了
he took an axe. He's dead.
我们没有败
We were not beaten.
哼，你想当威塞克斯国王，我可以允许
Hm. You want to become king of Wessex, I will allow that.
但我的报酬呢？我的银子？我的粮食？
But where is my payment? My silver? My grain?
- 说好了给的，现在却没了 - 都还在那儿
- It was promised, but now it has gone. - It's still there.
- 丹麦人不会输 - 我没有输
- Danes do not lose. - I am not lost.
你给了他们希望，古思伦，这比输了还糟
You have given them hope, Guthrum, that is worse.
没了国王，他们就没有希望
Without the king, there is no hope.
如果他们真的打败了丹麦人，当然我不相信是真的，那他们为什么不开宴庆功？
If they've defeated the Danes, which I won't believe, why aren't they feasting?
那个神父没说谎,
The priest doesn't lie,
尽管他只是个神父
despite him being a priest.
他们为什么这么不一样？
Why are they so different?
- 这么愁眉苦脸 - 天主的旨意
- So miserable. - God's wish.
我不会变成一个撒克逊女人,
I won't become a Saxon woman,
我不要洗衣、下地干活干到累死，还要做饭
I won't wash, work the fields until I drop and cook.
- 不会走到那一步的 - 那不会是我的日子
- It won't come to that. - That won't be my life.
阿尔弗雷德能帮我们，我们可以利用他...
Alfred can help us. We'll use him...
先借他的地方落脚，再从他那儿捞财富
for shelter, and then for wealth.
- 他利用了你 - 现在他欠我的
- He has used you. - And now he owes me.
早上好
Good morning.
谢谢你昨晚的款待
My thanks for last night.
开门，我要见我父亲
Open the door, I wish to see my father.
开门，否则我割下你的蛋蛋当弹弓用
Open the door, or I'll have your balls for sling-shot.
埃塞尔沃尔德
Aethelwold.
我来为父亲祈祷，陪在他身边
I am here to pray for my father, to be at his side.
国王已经驾崩了
The king is dead.
为何没人来叫我？我本应陪在他身边的
Why was I not called? I should have been at his side.
- 找不到你 - 我就在自己的寝室里睡觉
- You could not be found. - I was sleeping in my chamber.
国王临终前，指定我为王位继承人
Before he passed, the king named me as heir to the throne.
他亲口告诉我的
That's what he told me.
这是实情
It's the truth.
这是他最后的心愿
His last wish.
这是他最后的旨意
His last command.
你们最好都把这话传出去
You would all do well to repeat this.
我会将你的主张禀报贤人会议
I'll inform the Witan of your claim.
- 你应该这么做 - 不过在场所有人，还有更多人，
- You should. - Although each person here, and more,
都亲耳听见你父亲将王冠传给了阿尔弗雷德
heard your father bequeath his crown to Alfred.
他那时候神志不清
He must have been delirious.
什么时候？
On which occasion?
我是国王的儿子
I am the son of the king.
做好你的本职工作
Do your duty.
- 大人 - 啊，乌特雷德
- My lord. - Ah. Uhtred,
请接受我的道歉，让你延缓释放，我有事缠身
please accept my apology for the delay in your release. I had matters to attend.
要来点麦酒吗，神父？
Ale, Father?
来一点，也给我们的客人倒上
A little, and for our guests.
- 看来你说的是实话 - 我说的确实是实话
- (ALFRED) It seems you spoke the truth. - I did.
虽然我清楚这次胜利只是暂时的
Though I realise our victory is temporary,
我欠你的情，威塞克斯也欠你的情
I am indebted, Wessex is indebted.
- 我的道歉够吗？ - 不够，大人
- Is my apology enough? - It is not, lord.
乌特雷德的意思是，道歉根本没有必要
What Uhtred means is that it is not necessary.
我希望能像郡长一样被对待，因为我本来就是
I wish to be seen as an ealdorman, because I am.
- 那是在诺森布里亚，这里是威塞克斯 - 这里是英格兰
- In Northumbria. This is Wessex. - This is England.
你说过要建立一个统一的王国
One kingdom is what you said.
你现在什么土地都没有
You are without lands, completely.
那正是我要的，也是我应得的——土地
Then that's what I want. That's what I deserve, land.
我把你叫来只是想当面道谢
I brought you here solely to convey my thanks,
但我们迟些还会再谈
but we shall talk further at some point,
- 我还有事要处理 - 我给了你这场胜利，大人
- I have other matters to attend. - I gave you victory, lord,
- 还有什么比这更重要？ - 国王驾崩了
- what's more important? - (ALFRED) The king is dead.
- 什么时候的事？ - 我刚刚离开他
- Since when? - (ALFRED) I have not long left him.
我登基后的第一件事，就是向丹麦人提出和议
My first act as king will be to offer the Danes a peace.
他们会觉得你软弱无能
(BRIDA) They will think you spineless,
大人
Lord.
那我就得让他们改变这个想法
Then I must convince them otherwise.
姑娘，给我的寝室送些果子来，切好的苹果和牛奶
Girl, bring some fruits to my chamber, some chopped apples and milk.
好好休息，洗个澡，吃顿好的，你们赢得了这一切
Rest, wash, eat well, you have earned it.
你在说什么？跟未来的国王说话不能这副口气
What are you saying? You do not speak to a future king in that manner.
他不是我的领主，也不会是我的国王
He's not my lord and won't be my king.
听清楚了，乌特雷德，阿尔弗雷德才是值得追随的人
Hear me clearly, Uhtred. Alfred is the man to follow.
他是你回到贝班堡的路，你会以领主和主人的身份回去
He is your way back to Bebbanburg, as lord and master.
乌特雷德走哪条路是他自己的事
Uhtred's path is Uhtred's business,
轮不到一个神父来指手画脚
not that of a priest.
大人，请恕我失礼
Forgive me, lord,
我得先离开
I must leave,
去祈祷，求主赐我力量，好驱散这些盘踞心头的邪念
pray for strength and to expunge these unholy thoughts that fill my mind.
你想要威塞克斯的土地？
You want land in Wessex?
那是我回贝班堡的路
It's my way back to Bebbanburg.
你在阿尔弗雷德那边挣到的任何财银，丹麦人都会抢走
Any silver you End under Alfred will be taken by the Danes,
连你的命一起，他们根本打不过
along with your life. They can't be beaten.
- 你为什么要这么做？ - 我说了，为了财富
- Why are you doing this? - I've said, wealth.
大人，请借过
Excuse me, my lord,
我正要去给阿尔弗雷德大人跑腿
I am on an errand to my Lord Alfred.
- 这牛奶是给阿尔弗雷德的？ - 是的
- The milk is for Alfred? - It is.
不许说出去
Not a word.
去吧
Go on.
埃塞尔沃尔德公子
Master Aethelwold,
你这个妄想称王的毛头小子
the man-child who would have himself be king.
出于对先王的敬重，阿尔弗雷德不希望动你
Out of respect for the late king, Alfred wishes no to harm to be done
丑陋脑袋上的一根头发
to a hair of your ugly head,
但他绝不会容忍你的无礼和谎言
but he will not put up with your insolence and lies.
你自己的儿子也参与了我所谓的无礼
Your own son is party to my so called insolence.
闭嘴
(ODDA) Quiet!
不许把别人拖进你的阴谋
Don't you involve others in your Conspiracies.
我的脑袋又不丑
My head is not ugly.
你将被送往汉普顿的修道院
You're to be sent to Hampton, to a monastery,
接受教化，这是个漫长的过程
to be educated, it will be a long process.
我是国王的儿子
I am the king's son.
威塞克斯经不起内部分裂
(ODDA) Wessex cannot afford division.
也经不起一个蠢孩子的胡言乱语，不管他出身贵贱
Nor can it afford the ramblings of an idiot child, noble or otherwise.
去办吧
See to it.
我能让他老实点吗？——我巴不得你这样
(LEOFRIC) May I make him docile? (ODDA) I wish you would.
不，不，不！嗯！
(AETHELWOLD) No, no, no! Unh!
进来
(ALFRED) Come.
大人，您找我？
Lord, you wished to see me?
是的，是的
I did, I did.
你要去给古思伦，给丹麦人带个话
You will take a message to Guthrum, to the Danes.
邀请他们在近日内前来谈判
You will invite them to negotiate within days,
时间地点由他们定
but at their own convenience.
大人，若是要传话，宫里的人多的是
If it is a messenger you require, lord, there are plenty within the palace
我要的不是传话的人，是代我出面的人
It is not a messenger I require, it is a representative.
你替我说话
You will speak for me.
奥达，你代表我
Odda, you will speak as me.
跟丹麦人什么都不能写在纸上
Nothing can be written for the Danes.
我的书信已无意义,
My letters would be meaningless,
所以这些话必须由我亲口说出,
therefore the words spoken
必须是我的话,
must be my words,
我将它们托付于你
and I entrust them to you.
那我很乐意做你的使者,大人
Then I shall gladly be your representative, lord.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我盯着你看,冒犯你了吗?
Do I offend you? Watching you?
没有,大人,从来没有
No, my lord, never.
我会以命护你
I will defend you with my life.
你是最珍贵的存在,你就是威塞克斯,就是英格兰,
You stand as everything that's precious. You are Wessex, England,
永远值得珍视,永远不可侵犯,
always to be cherished, never to be violated,
只能深情地爱护
only to be loved vigorously.
- 谁啊? - 是我,大人
- Who is it? - (BEOCCA) My lord.
我的良心
My conscience.
大人,愿否与我一同为逝去的国王祈祷?
My lord, would you care to join me in prayer for the passing of the king?
好,神父,多谢你
I will, Father. I give you my thanks.
请见谅,大人,
Forgive me, my lord,
牛奶变质了
the milk has soured.
我受够奶和苹果了,我要吃肉
I am tired of milk and apples. I need meat.
但大人，你是一个殉教者，不能吃肉
But you are a martyr, my lord, to meat.
领主大人也需要吃饱
My lord needs feeding.
领主大人不是圣人,也永远不会是
My lord is not a saint and never shall be.
我从战场上幸存下来,我需要吃肉
I have survived battle, I need meat.
我们一起祈祷吧,大人,祈求力量
We shall pray together, my lord, for strength.
为什么这也算是罪?
Why does it have to be a sin?
这已经是个重担了
Already, it is a burden.
好像从来都不是我想做什么
It seems never to be about what I would wish to do,
而是我必须做什么
it is about what I must do.
求天主赐我力量, 让我能像你一样戴好这顶王冠
Ask God to give me the strength to wear the crown as well as you.
贝奥卡神父
Father Beocca.
- 稍等- 是, 大人
- A moment. - Yes, lord.
乌特雷德或许还有用处
Uhtred may well have a use.
我很高兴您能这么想 大人
I'm pleased that is what you think, lord.
这个布丽达, 她跟他是什么关系?
This Brida, she is what to him?
- 我说是个累赘- 妻子?
- I would say a hindrance. - A wife?
- 不不, 绝对不是- 她坐立不安
- No, no. Never, no. - She is restless.
- 她是他肩上的恶魔, 我担心- 但他很在乎她
- She is the devil on his shoulder, I fear. - But he is fond of her.
是啊, 他就是这种人
Yes, that is his way.
走着瞧吧
We shall see.
- 谢谢- 大人
- Thank you. - My lord.
我带来一封信
(YOUNGER) I carry a message.
- 来自阿尔弗雷德国王- 阿尔弗雷德国王是谁?
- From King Alfred. - Who is King Alfred?
他是威塞克斯国王阿尔弗雷德
He is, Alfred, King of Wessex.
他邀请古思伦伯爵前来谈和
He invites the Earl Guthrum to negotiate a peace.
你就是古思伦?
You are Guthrum?
从马上下来, 小子
Get down from your horse, boy.
从马上下来, 好好看看我
Get down from your horse and look at me.
你长得不错嘛
You are a beauty.
告诉那个国王, 他叫什么来着?
Tell this king, what was his name?
阿尔弗雷德
Alfred.
告诉阿尔弗雷德国王, 古思伦接受他的邀请,
Tell King Alfred that Guthrum accepts his invitation,
我会在路上等候, 亲自出迎
and I will watch for him and I shall ride out and meet him.
我会转达您的话, 大人
I will pass on your message, lord.
这匹马现在是我的了
This horse belongs to me now.
乌特雷德, 阿尔弗雷德很想重用你
Uhtred, Alfred is keen to find a use for you,
但布丽达……她只会添乱
but Brida is... She's not a help.
你能不能让她离他远一点
Perhaps you could just keep her away from him.
阿尔弗雷德知道我能派上用场, 我已经证明过了
Alfred knows I can be of use, and I have proven it.
现在轮到他证明他对我有用了
Now he must prove he can be of use to me.
- 他将会成为国王 - 你可以效忠于他
- He will be king. - And you can serve him.
我来这里是为了我自己
I'm here to serve myself.
阿尔弗雷德对我来说不过是一条路，让我夺回失去的一切
Alfred means nothing but a path to take back what is mine.
我的土地, 我的财富, 还有我的封号
My land, my wealth, and my title.
他能用上我, 但我也能用上他
He will have a use for me, but I will have a use for him.
别小看他, 他会把你看穿的
Do not think him naive. He will see right through you.
他只会看到我想让他看到的东西
He will see what I allow him to see.
听着, 乌特雷德, 你现在是个战士, 不是谋士
Look, Uhtred, right now you are a warrior, not a thinker.
不过假以时日, 这一点也会来的
Though, in time, this will come.
你很像你父亲, 而他两者兼备
You are much like your father, and he was both.
你现在是阿尔弗雷德的神父了, 贝奥卡
You are AIfred's priest now, Beocca.
想找人作伴吗, 姑娘?
(LEOFRIC) You looking for company, girl?
我宁可与众神为伴, 也不愿跟蠢货待在一起
I prefer the company of the gods to stupid men.
那改天吧?
Another time, then?
- 早安, 乌特雷德 - 早安, 大人
- Good morning, Uhtred. - (UHTRED) Good morning, lord.
- 好一件锁子甲 - 是的
- That's a fine coat of mail. - (ALFRED) It is.
这是你的了, 一套撒克逊武士的战甲, 送给你的
And it is yours, the battle dress of a Saxon warrior. A gift.
换什么? 凡事都有代价
(UHTRED) In return for what? There's always a price.
你已经付清了
(ALFRED) Which you have paid in full.
那场山岗上的胜仗
Our victory at the hill.
小奥达, 你向乌特雷德道歉了吗?
Young Odda, have you offered your apologies to Uhtred?
我真心道歉, 你说的是实话
My sincere apologies, you spoke the truth.
稍微鞠个躬, 也许?
A small bow, perhaps?
你可以退下了
You may leave us now.
一个好国王要善于听取良言, 乌特雷德
A good king relies upon good advice, Uhtred.
比如我的侄子埃塞尔沃尔德, 先王之子,
For example, my nephew, Aethelwold, the king's son,
他年纪轻轻却自认是理所当然的王位继承人
he is young but sees himself as the rightful heir.
我该怎么处置他?
How am I to deal with him?
您应该杀了他, 大人,
You should kill him, lord,
就像我叔父埃尔弗里克想杀我一样
as my own uncle, Aelfric, would kill me.
- 不杀他就是示弱 - 你太放肆了
- Not to kill him shows weakness. - You are being insolent.
我允许他这样说,
I will allow it,
这是他骨子里的异教徒在说话
it is the pagan in him speaking.
你的思维方式像个丹麦人, 乌特雷德
You think like a Dane, Uhtred.
我若杀了埃塞尔沃尔德, 就等于承认他对王位有正当的主张,
If I kill Aethelwold, I am admitting he has legitimate claim to the throne,
而他并没有, 这才是我的想法
which he does not. That is how I think.
不过, 在议会里留一个异教徒的头脑倒是有用
But to have a specimen of the heathen mind in council will be useful.
丹麦人最怕什么?
What do they fear most, the Danes?
他们是战士, 生来就为战斗
They're warriors, live to fight.
但要是打了败仗, 就像那场山岗之战, 然后呢?
But when they lose, as at the hill, what then?
打仗时, 他们宁可撤退也不愿损兵折将
In battle, they'd rather retreat than lose too many men.
如果他们有什么畏惧的,那就是折损人马
If they fear anything at all, it is losing men.
他们嗜战,却不甘认败,
They love to fight but hate to lose,
这倒不算什么新鲜事
hardly a revelation.
奥达似乎不把你的意见放在眼里
Odda appears not to value your council.
- 确实不放- 我也无所谓
- (ODDA) I do not. - I care not.
你请求被认定为郡长一事,我一直在考虑
I have been thinking on your request to be recognised as an ealdorman.
- 简直是无稽之谈- 我本就是郡长
- (ODDA) Which is a nonsense. - I am an ealdorman.
你名下连一只羊都没有,更别提放牧的土地了
Without a goat to your name, never mind the land to graze it.
- 我是郡长- 你可否考虑
- I'm an ealdorman. - Would you consider
以联姻的方式成为郡长?
becoming an ealdorman by marriage?
我知道有门亲事,能给你带来土地和头衔
I know of a marriage that would bring you land and title.
- 我不需要妻子，大人     - 妻子能对你有帮助  - 变老？
- I have no need of a wife,lord - A woman helps you grow.  -Grow old？
扎下根来,这正是你所欠缺的
Grow roots, and that is what you are missing.
婚姻能证明你对威塞克斯的忠心
Marriage would show your commitment, to Wessex.
我已经证明过了
I have shown commitment.
您自己也说过,是我给了您这场在山岭的胜利
You've said yourself, I gave you victory at the hill.
你出了力,但这场胜利是威塞克斯的战士打下来的
You helped, but the victory was won by the men of Wessex.
而你如今却拒绝通过这门婚事融入他们
Whom you now refuse to join through this marriage.
土地和银子是每个男人都想要的,我也不例外
Land and silver is what all men desire and I'm no different.
但请相信我,大人,我不需要妻子
But believe me, lord, I have no need of a wife.
- 我的剑为您效命   - 但有条件
- My sword is yours. - (ODDA) At a price?
我所拥有的一切都被人夺走了
Everything that I have has been taken from me.
我需要头衔,需要积攒自己的财富
I need title, I need to make my wealth.
你是打算为我效忠，还是只是当一个雇佣兵?
Are you are offering me your sword or are you selling me your sword?
要成为郡长,你必须拥有土地,
To become an ealdorman you must possess land,
这是法令       但如果在接下来的谈判中
that is the law. However, stand at my side
你站在我这边, 帮我看透对手
during the negotiations ahead, help me read my enemy
作为回报
and in return
我们再好好谈谈赏赐的事
we shall talk further of wealth and reward.
那么, 你看到什么了?
Well, what did you see?
- 他们让你看到了什么? - 我看到的是我自己的事
- What did they show you? - What I saw is my business.
我感觉不舒服
I feel unwell.
来
Here.
水
Water.
我们身处此地是命运的安排
Where we find ourselves is fate,
是那三位纺者的旨意
the work of the three spinners,
她们深藏在我们脚下的大地里, 是她们把我们带到了这里
they sit deep in this earth beneath us and they have brought us here.
我们该走了...
We should go...
去康沃卢姆
To Cornwalum,
威尔士, 爱尔兰
Wales, Ireland,
- 去哪儿都行 - 为什么?
- anywhere. - Why?
逃离这里
Escape.
为了安全
Safety.
我看见了拉格纳的船
I saw Ragnar's ship.
- 往事号吗? - 不, 是风蛇号
- The past? - No. Wind Viper.
是小拉格纳?
Young Ragnar?
我就在那船上, 我亲眼看见的
I was there on the ship. I saw it.
我想离开这里
I want to leave here.
跟我来
Come with me.
我已经向阿尔弗雷德许下承诺
I've given a promise to Alfred.
出席谈判, 出谋划策
To attend the negotiations, to advise.
布丽达, 我们无处可去
Bride, there's no place else for us to go.
我们不能留在这里
We cannot stay here.
这是个开始
It's a beginning.
你走吧
Leave me.
我们不能就这样在各处流荡, 什么都不做
We cannot wander the country and do nothing.
你怎么能信任他?
How can you trust him?
你怎么知道他不会把你直接交给古思伦
How do you know he won't simply turn you over to Guthrum
再转交给乌巴? 你对他一无所知
to pass on to Ubba? You know nothing about him.
我信任贝奥卡神父, 而贝奥卡是他的神父
I trust Father Beocca, and Beocca is his priest.
我说了, 走开
I said leave me.
你没有和我一起在那条船上!
You were not on the ship with me!
去找阿尔弗雷德吧, 我倒要亲眼看他怎么出卖你!
Go to Alfred, and I will watch him betray you!
那么, 我们对这个阿尔弗雷德了解多少?
So, what do we know of this Alfred?
他体弱多病, 软弱无能
That he is sickly, he's weak.
他想要谈判
He wants to negotiate.
看来他根本不是个战士
Turns out that he's no warrior.
- 但他打败了你, 古思伦 - 哈哈哈
- But he beat you, Guthrum. - (GUTHRUM) Heh, heh, heh.
那上面写的什么?
So, what does it say?
谈判
Negotiation.
白银
Silver.
我们会拿走他的白银
We will take his silver
还有他的土地
and his land.
他若拒绝呢?他绝不会拒绝的
(GUTHRUM) And If he refuses? (UBBA) He will never refuse.
他想活命, 也想被称为国王, 哈哈哈
He wants to live and he wants to be called king. Heh, heh, heh.
天主在天之灵,
Our God in his heaven,
求你垂顾你忠心的仆人阿尔弗雷德
we ask you to find favour with your devoted servant, Alfred.
赐他勇气、力量与智慧
Bless him with courage, strength and wisdom.
永不离他左右, 阿门
Never leave his side. Amen.
阿门
(ALL) Amen.
赐他纯洁神圣的心念,
(SELBIX) Allow him pure and holy thoughts,
赐他能力, 以吾王之身在世间完成你的旨意
and the power to carry out your work on this earth as our king.
愿这涂油礼成就你的意志, 降福于阿尔弗雷德
Allow this anointing of Alfred to enable your will.
你是天主选立的国王, 威塞克斯的阿尔弗雷德
You are God's king, Alfred of Wessex.
阿尔佛雷德国王万岁
Vivat Rex alfredus!
没有你的日子, 我难以想象
I can't imagine a time without you.
阿尔佛雷德国王万岁
Vivat Rex alfredus!
那是古思伦?
It is Guthrum?
是
Yes.
你看他头发里夹着一根骨头
You can see a bone in his hair.
那是他母亲的肋骨
It's his mother's rib.
真叫人动容
How endearing.
其他人呢?
And the others?
那是乌巴, 那个大块头
(UHTRED) It is Ubba. The big man.
首领乌巴也来了?
The Chieftain, Ubba, is with them?
你说他在北边
You said he was in the north.
他现在在这儿
(ALFRED) Now he is here.
这倒是好事
This is good.
所以你就是阿尔弗雷德,
(GUTHRUM) So you are Alfred,
- 威塞克斯的国王? - 正是
-the king of Wessex? - (ALFRED) I am.
- 你是古思伦伯爵? - 是的
- You are Earl Guthrum? - Yes.
若想要和平, 你得付出代价
If you want peace, you'll have to pay.
你就是乌巴伯爵
And you are the Earl Ubba.
- 欢迎 - 说吧
- Welcome. - Speak.
以商定数量的粮食、牲畜和银两为交换,
In exchange for an agreed amount of grain, livestock and silver,
我提议你们率船队返回伦敦, 并留守于此
I propose that you and your ships return to Lundene and remain there.
我还提议你们将活动范围限于东盎格利亚,
I further propose you confine yourselves to East Anglia,
麦西亚和诺森布里亚
Mercia and Northumbria.
威塞克斯是撒克逊人的土地, 因此对所有丹麦人禁止踏入
Wessex is Saxon, and as such out-of-bounds to all Danes.
我们不会离开威塞克斯的
We'll not be leaving Wessex.
我们才刚到
We only just arrived.
那你们就等着挨饿吧
Then you will starve.
你们粮食匮乏,
You have little food,
没有栖身之所, 军队也已大伤元气
no shelter and a weakened army.
若你觉得我们已是强弩之末, 为何还要求和?
If you believe us weakened, why seek peace?
这是我身为基督徒的本性
It is the Christian in me.
是我主的旨意
The will of my God.
- 哼, 我不想听什么神的说辞 - 是天主, 只有唯一的天主
- Oh, I will hear no talk of gods. - God. There is only one.
你该谈的是粮食,
You will talk of grain,
- 马匹、银两和土地 - 土地的事, 免谈
- horses, silver and land. - I will not talk of land.
他们在写什么?
What do they write?
他们在记录我们说的话
(ALFRED) They write what we speak.
- 每一个字? - 是的, 每一个字
- Every word? - Yes, every word.
那我要是说屁股
Then may I say arse,
乳房、做爱和狗屎呢
tits, hump and turd.
他们记录历史，我们在这里创造历史
They record history. We are here creating history.
后人会读到这场会面
People will read of this very meeting.
我在等你们投降
I'm waiting to hear your surrender.
你们退回伦敦，我们会给你们报酬
You will be paid for your return to Lundene.
其他就没什么好谈的，我们不会投降
There are no more terms and there will be no surrender.
古思伦不会离开雷丁厄姆
Guthrum here will not leave Readingum.
那我就再说一遍，他会饿死的
Then I say again, he will starve.
我们会突袭
(GUTHRUM) we win raid.
我们会杀人
We will kill.
那你们还会再折损人马
And you will lose yet more men.
这是你想要的吗，古思伦伯爵,
Is that your wish, Earl Guthrum,
折损兵力?
to lose men?
你剩下的勇士们或许会去另寻新主
Your surviving warriors may look to find a new lord.
你召集这次会面就是来羞辱我的?
Did you call a meeting to insult me?
我带来的是和平和事实
I offer peace and I offer facts.
拿他的人头来，你就能得到和平
(UBBA) His head, and you can have your peace.
就是他
Him.
乌特雷德 拉格纳松
Uhtred Ragnarson.
叛徒
A traitor.
- 无话可说? - 我只会跟小拉格纳谈
- Nothing to say? - I'll speak to young Ragnar.
其他的丹麦人不值得我的敬重
No other Dane has my respect.
用他的人头换和平
His head, for peace.
你要乌特雷德的人头来换和平?
You want Uhtred here for peace?
不要金银，不要粮草，不要马匹?
No silver, no grain, no horses?
我们要白银,还要叛徒的脑袋
We want silver, and the traitors head.
这就是条件还有你,阿尔弗雷德,哈,
These are the terms. And you, Alfred, heh,
你可以继续当国王,
you may remain king,
但我们要占领所有撒克逊人的要塞
but we will occupy all of the Saxon forts.
你们想占要塞,就去占,拿去
If you wish to occupy the fortresses, then do it, take them.
你们到目前为止拿下过几座?
How many have you taken to date?
- 他们到目前为止拿下过几座? - 一座都没有,大人
- How many have they taken to date? - None, lord.
我们随时可以拿下所有要塞!
We can take all fortresses at any time!
整个英格兰都是我们打下来的
We have taken the whole of England.
威塞克斯也一样
And we can do the same with Wessex.
我把话说清楚
Let me be clear.
我已经准备好重新开战，我们人比你们多
I'm prepared to return to the sword. We outnumber you.
我们人多势众,战力凶悍,但我更愿意谈和
We are many and we are dangerous, but I would prefer to establish a peace.
乌特雷德也会保住他的人头
And Uhtred here shall keep his head,
但我会给你们一大笔钱,换你们离开威塞克斯
but I will pay you well to leave Wessex.
这就是后人会读到的
That is what people will read.
阿尔弗雷德寻求和平
That Alfred sought peace.
阿尔弗雷德向乌巴大人和古思伦大人献上白银,以换取和平
Alfred paid Lords Ubba and Guthrum in silver in exchange for peace.
是我主动要结束这场仗的
It is I who is seeking an end to the fighting.
就这样写下去
That is what will be written.
乌特雷德
Uhtred.
我绝不会把你交给乌巴
I would never have given you up to Ubba.
但你确实有过这个想法,大人
But the thought did cross your mind, lord.
从来没有
Not once.
事实是,
The fact is,
我希望你宣誓效忠,
I would like you to swear an oath,
以圣物为证, 效力一年
on holy relics, a years' service.
期间你要帮助我的战士明白
During which time you will help my warriors understand
那些异教徒不过也是血肉之躯,
that the heathens are but men,
作为回报, 假以时日,
and in return, and in time,
你会得到应有的报酬
you shall have your own reward.
贝班堡的乌特雷德
Uhtred of Bebbanburg.
一年
One year.
孩子
(MAN) Boy.
给国王带去
For the king.
他们被拦住了, 但也仅此而已
(ALFRED) They have been halted, but nothing more.
他们还没有被打败
They are not defeated.
我们眼下的任务, 说简单简单, 说难也难
Our task now is both simple and impossible.
- 我们得摸清他们的动向 - 丹麦人的做法就一个字, 打
- We determine what they will do. - They will do what Danes do, attack.
怎么打? 在哪打? 何时打? 来多少人?
(ALFRED) How? Where? When? How many?
我们本该庆祝和平的, 非得谈打仗吗?
We're supposed to be Celebrating peace, do we have to talk of fighting?
必须谈, 亲爱的, 因为这份和平撑不久
(ALFRED) We do, my dear, because the peace will not last.
他们至少还需要一年才能集结起第二支大军
It'll take at least a year before they can gather a second great army.
- 你能保证吗? - 儿子
(YOUNGER) Do we have your word? (ODDA) Son.
这儿有肉吃吗?
Is there any meat here?
- 她该来这里吗? - 布丽达是我的客人
- Should she even be here? - Bride is my guest.
你早该接受国王给你赐婚的好意
You should have taken up the king's offer of a wife.
一位贵女
A lady.
接下来会发生的事, 就是他们从陆路和海上同时来犯
(ALFRED) What happens next is that they will come by land and sea.
他们会把我们的军队分割成两路, 甚至更多
They will split our army in two, possibly more.
乌特雷德说的也许没错，这事可能一年内不会发生，甚至更久
Now, Uhtred may be correct, this may not occur for a year or more,
但有一点是清楚的——我们需要船
but what is clear is that we need ships.
四面环水，我们的船却少得可怜
We are bordered by water, yet we have so few ships.
别指望我上船
You'll not get me on a ship.
我可以让我儿子去
I'll volunteer my son.
要守住我们的海岸，就得把目光放到海岸之外
To save our shores, we have to look beyond them,
而且为了侍奉天主
and to serve God,
- 祂的圣言必须远播 - 阿门，颂主荣耀
- his word must travel. - Amen. Praise him.
乌特雷德，丹麦人船头的那些怪兽
Uhtred, the beasts,
on the prows of Danes' ships,
是他们神明的象征吗
they are a representation of their gods?
不，大人，不过就是兽头装饰
No, lord. They are just beasts.
靠近陆地时可以卸下来，免得惊扰到土地上的神灵
They can be lifted, so not to frighten the spirits of the land.
土地的神灵，哈哈
Spirits of the land. Heh, heh.
我倒想知道，他们为什么有人要把自己的牙磨尖
I'd like to know why some of them make their own teeth into points.
- 真有这回事？ - 有些人会这样，夫人
- They do that? - Some, lady.
愿主保佑我们
(AELSWITH) God save us.
这是为了证明自己不怕痛
To show that they aren't afraid.
连自己都能下得了手，你想想他们会怎么对付撒克逊人
If they can inflict pain on themselves, think what they can do to a Saxon.
我相信我们对他们的了解会与日俱增
(ALFRED) We will understand them more by the day, I'm sure.
丹麦人乌特雷德已经答应为我效力一年
Uhtred of the Danes has promised me a year of his service.
是吗
Is that so?
是的
It is.
他的责任就是让我们的战士了解
It will be his responsibility to show our warriors
丹麦人是如何迎战的
how the Danes approach battle,
还有盾墙的布阵之法
the construction of their shield wall, and the like.
大人 恕我冒昧的说一句
Lord, if I may,
这浑球还不过是个毛头小子, 你指望他来教我打仗?
The arseling here is barely a man, you expect him to teach me to fight?
利奥弗里克, 我可没指望他教你什么
Leofric, I expect him to teach you nothing.
练兵时你尽管拿棍子抽他
Whip him with staves in practise by all means.
好的 大人
(LEOFRIC) Thank you, lord.
但是
But,
但我手下那些普通兵士,
our lesser men,
若他们能摸透丹麦人的门道,
if they can know what a Dane knows,
恐惧就会被知识驱散
fear can be expelled with knowledge,
不管敌人的牙有多利
regardless how sharp their teeth.
你今晚没吃东西
You didn't eat tonight.
吃了也只会吐出来
I'd only throw it up.
一年?
A year?
现在是定了一年, 说不定就是一辈子
It starts with a year and becomes a lifetime.
他还给你许了门亲事?
And he offered you a wife?
我不需要娶妻
I have no need of a wife.
但你却宣誓要去杀丹麦人
Instead you swore an oath to kill Danes.
你知道我这么做的原因
You know my reasons.
我们一直住在王宫里
We have been living in a palace.
要是你在战场上
What happens if you find yourself
碰上了小拉格纳, 怎么办?
facing young Ragnar in battle?
那就和他打
We fight.
她在哪儿?
Where is she?
- 今早一直没听到她的动静 - 她走不远的
- I haven't heard her all morning. - She'll not be far.
好了,我们快要出发了
Well, we're about to leave.
我看到了
I can see.
我随后就来
I'll follow.
布丽达!
(UHTRED) Bridal
Bridal
布丽达!
布丽达?
Bdda?
几乎快成形了
Almost a child.
- 你知道吗? - 嗯?
- You knew? - Hm?
你知道自己有身孕?
That you were carrying?
不知道
(BRIDA) No.
你在梦里没有看到吗,
You didn't see it in your dreams,
你喝了蘑菇麦酒的时候
when you drank the mushroom ale.
我来埋了它
I'll bury it.
我们一起埋 这是逝去的征兆
We will bury it. It is a sign of a passing.
- 并肩而立! - 盾牌向前!
- Stand together! - (UHTRED) Shields front!
举起盾牌! 盾牌靠拢!
(LEOFRIC) Shields up! (UHTRED) Shields together!
- 盯住他们的眼睛! - 靠紧些! 坚不可摧!
- Look them in the eye! - Closer together! Unbreakable!
准备好了吗? 准备好了!
Are we ready? Yeah!
- 我说,准备好了吗? - 前进!
- I said, are we ready? - Forward!
准备好了!
Yeah!
- 杀了这些混蛋! - 并肩而立!
- Kill the bastards! - Stand together!
盾牌靠拢!
Shields together!
用盾猛砸他们! 盾是我们的护甲, 也是我们的武器!
We hammer them with our shields! They are our defence and our weapon!
把他们撞倒在地!
We knock them off their feet!
我们就是一堵墙!
We are a wall!
冲!
Charge!
两排盾墙交锋之前,
Before the two walls meet,
前三排士兵必须协同配合, 筑起一道高耸的盾墙
the first three rows of men act together, to create a tall shield wall.
第一排蹲低, 护住下腹和双腿
First row crouches lower, protecting the lower body and legs.
第二排前伸, 护住上身
The second row reaches forward, protecting the upper body.
第三排压上, 护住所有人的头顶
The third row leans in, protecting the head of all rows of men.
举盾!
Shields up.
盾牌靠拢!
Shields together!
立盾墙!
Shield Wall!
不赖嘛, 浑球
I like it, arseling.
真的不错
I do.
现在, 杀了那帮混蛋!
Now, kill the bastards!
这些财物不是我的,
(BRIDA) The wealth is not mine,
是无畏的拉格纳大人的
it belongs to Lord Ragnar, the fearless.
你最好离我远点
You will do well to leave me alone.
你是布丽达?
(MAN) Are you Brida?
谁在问?
Who asks?
- 布丽达 - 她怎么了?
- Brida. - What of her?
我不是先知,
I'm no seer,
但我看得出她过得不开心
but I'd say she's unhappy.
她更喜欢和丹麦人待在一起, 不喜欢撒克逊人,
She prefers the company of Danes to Saxons,
这没什么问题
nothing wrong in that.
她跟的那些撒克逊人不是好货
She's been with the wrong Saxons.
- 丹麦人对生活有股劲 - 谁没有呢?
- The Danes have a hunger for life. - Don't we all?
阿尔弗雷德...
Alfred...
他是个认真的人
He's serious.
虔诚的混蛋
A pious bastard.
你可以不喜欢他,
Dislike him, by all means,
但千万别小看他
but never underestimate him.
他心狠手辣,
He's ruthless,
而且脑子好使,
and the man thinks,
这一点你我都比不上
which is more than you or I could do.
战士利奥弗里克,
Leofric the warrior,
我能坐你旁边吗?
may I sit with you?
不行
No, you may not.
修道院的僧侣们知道你跑出来了吗?
Do the monks know you're missing?
乌特雷德, 这是埃塞尔沃尔德, 又一个浑球
Uhtred, this is Aethelwold, another arseling.
- 国王的侄子 - 不, 我不是国王的侄子
- Nephew of the king. - No, I am not the nephew of the king.
我才是国王
I am the king.
但阿尔弗雷德喜欢装模作样,
But Alfred likes to pretend,
每个浑蛋都乐意配合他演这出戏, 哈哈
and every bastard appears to be happy with the lie. Heh, heh.
- 咱们在说什么? - 阿尔弗雷德
- What are we talking about? - Alfred.
他不让我上战场, 我跟你说过吗?
He will not allow me to fight. Have I told you that?
- 说过很多次了 - 反正是真的
- Many times. - Well, it's true.
他就是不让我打仗
He will not allow me to fight.
利奥弗里克, 勇士, 我想请你
I would like you, warrior Leofric,
教我怎么打仗, 我来教你怎么...
to teach me how to fight and I shall teach you how to...
- 继续说 - 你可别忘了付钱
- (LEOFRIC) Go on. - You will not forget to pay for this.
我有忘过吗?
Have I ever?
有过一两次
Once or twice.
阿尔弗雷德有次被抓到跟修女鬼混
Alfred was caught humping a nun once.
我真该一刀捅了他的喉咙
(AETHELWOLD) What I ought to do is slit his gizzard. Unh!
这话要是让别人听见, 小子, 你就得上绞架
(LEOFRIC) Say that to anyone but me, boy, and you'll be hanged.
你这是在伤害皇室血脉
(AETHELWOLD) You are hurting royalty.
你应该庆幸阿尔弗雷德没杀你
You are lucky Alfred hasn't had you killed.
天主不会允许他那样做
God will not allow him.
我挺喜欢天主的
I like God.
银子
Silver.
对
Yes.
为什么?
Why?
- 你要离开我 - 你喝多了?
- You leaving me. - Are you drunk?
也许有一点
Maybe a little.
我们把这些银子给小拉格纳
We will give the silver to young Ragnar.
明天
Tomorrow.
黄昏时分
Dusk.
他来了
He's here.
我们可以告诉他实情,
We can tell him the truth,
然后加入拉格纳和他的人马
and we can join Ragnar and his men.
我需要的人, 要被天主、职责、土地、威塞克斯本身所束缚
I need men bound to me by God, by duty, by the land, by Wessex itself.
我想再次向乌特雷德提出联姻的事
I would again like to put to Uhtred the prospect of marriage.
- 嫁给我的教女? - 是的, 米尔德丝
- To my goddaughter? - To Mildrith, yes.
这确实能让他与这片土地紧密相连
Well, it would certainly bind him to the land,
也间接地与教会和天主紧密相连
and indirectly to the church, to God.
- 这是对他的考验 - 没错
- It would test him. - It would.
你还是愿意支持吗?
You would be in favour still?
当然
Of course.
为了威塞克斯, 什么都值得
Anything for Wessex.
成为乌特雷德 拉格纳松这个身份是不错的
Uhtred Ragnarson is a good man to be.
看着我
Look at me.
你什么都不欠阿尔弗雷德
You owe Alfred nothing.
在他眼里, 你的誓言一文不值, 因为你是个异教徒
To him, your word means nothing, you are a pagan.
求你了
Please.
乌特雷德 拉格纳松永远成不了贝班堡的乌特雷德
Uhtred Ragnarson can never become Uhtred of Bebbanburg.
永远不会
Never.
是你杀了我父亲吗?
Did you kill my father?
你还用问?
You need to ask?
是你杀了我的家人吗?
Did you kill my family?
他没有
He didn't.
我和乌特雷德说话
I am speaking with Uhtred.
我不会问第二遍
I won't ask a second time.
如果你以为是我杀了咱们的父亲,
If you believe that I would kill our father,
咱们的母亲,
our mother,
还有咱们的家人...
and our family...
那就来报仇吧
Take your revenge.
我就知道
I knew it.
我必须确认一下, 但我就知道
I had to be sure, I knew it.
是基尔坦干的
It was Kjartan.
是基尔坦发动了袭击, 放的火
Kjartan attacked and set the fire.
- 要是能救他们, 我们早救了 - 我就知道
- If we could have saved them, we would. - I knew it.
那些话我一个字都没信
I didn't believe a word I was hearing.
拉格纳的财富都在我们手里
We have Ragnar's wealth.
我们一直替你保管着
We kept it for you.
- 布丽达, 都长大成人了 - 嘿嘿嘿
- Bride. A fully grown woman now. - Heh, heh, heh.
这一刻我在梦里见过太多次了
I've seen this moment in my dreams so many times.
基尔坦的说法是英格兰人在你的鼓励下起来反抗咱们的父亲,
So Kjartan's story is that the English rose against our father,
encouraged by you.
他声称自己已经为那些杀手报了仇
He claims to have revenged himself for the killers.
你有相信过他吗?
Did you ever believe him?
从没信过
Never.
但他现在是基尔坦大人了
But he is Lord Kjartan now.
手下的人是咱们的三倍, 还有乌巴撑腰
He has three times the men, and the ear of Ubba.
嗯
Hm.
我要杀他, 得好好谋划
When I kill him, it will need to be planned.
是我们一起杀他
When we kill him.
- 这会很危险 - 但必须去做
- It will be dangerous. - It must be done.
拉格纳, 我们与你同在
Ragnar, we're with you.
那你们愿意随我出航?
Then you will sail with me?
愿意
I Will.
我已向阿尔弗雷德宣过誓
I have sworn to Alfred.
那算不了什么
It means nothing.
好吧你既然已经发过誓...
Well, if you have sworn...
就得说话算数
Then you must keep your word.
这份复仇对我来说, 如同水一般不可或缺
I need this revenge like I need water.
时机成熟之时, 我发誓我一定与你并肩
When the time is right, I swear I will be with you.
我知道
I know.
真不敢相信我就要放你离开了
I can't believe I'm about to let you go.
就这么失去你
Lose you.
你已经成为我一半的生命
You have been half my life.
全部的疯狂
All of my madness.
过的开心点
Be happy.
她走了吧?
(LEOFRIC) I take it she has gone then?
我猜阿尔弗雷德是让你选择留下的原因
I'm guessing that's it's Alfred that kept you here.
我为了一件锁甲和一顶头盔
I sold myself.
出卖了自己
For a mail coat and helmet.
我们都是这样, 把自己出卖出去
That's what we do, we sell ourselves.
今年这一年,
This year,
你要为阿尔弗雷德付出的, 和锁甲没关系
what you've giving to Alfred, it's not about a mail coat.
和你自己有关
It's about you.
这混蛋很聪明, 我没说错吧?
The bastard thinks, didn't I say?
他要的不只是一年的效力
He wants more than a year's service.
他要你帮他夺回英格兰
He wants you to help take back England.
整个英格兰
All of England.
当然, 等一年期满, 你可以回丹麦人那边去
Of course, when the year's up, you could go back to the Danes.
那样我至少有机会杀了你
That would at least give me the chance to kill you.
但你会成为什么?
But what would you be?
你又会是谁?
Who would you be?